Hello everyone and welcome back to
active inference insights. I'm your host
Darius Pavizy Wayne. And today I'm
thrilled to be speaking with Connor
Hines. Connor is a PhD student although
he just told me he just finished his PhD
at the Max Planck Institute of animal
behavior as well as a researcher at
Versus AI. His work focuses on the
apparent teleology of complex systems
and especially how they can be described
as conducting variational Bayesian
inference over their environments. Thus
Connor leans heavily on active inference
and the free energy principle in his
analysis of collective behavioral
systems. So he's the perfect guest for
today's episode. Connor, thank you so
much for being here. I'm super excited
to learn from you. Um I need to put my
technical hat on because your papers are
are technical um but I think there's a
lot that non-technical audiences will be
able to get out of them.
Yeah, thanks so much for having me. No,
no. It's It's genuinely It's absolutely
my pleasure. Um
I feel like psychology or cognitive
science likes taking the unit of
analysis as the individual.
And then saying, "Okay, how can we
extrapolate from the individual to
describe group dynamics?"
So I want to start very broadly with a
kind of axiomatic question about when
you uh study collective systems.
Is there a difference between collective
behavior in and of itself like what you
talk about in terms of collective
behavior and then the behavior of an
aggregation of individuals who we can
say belong to a group?
So is there something over and above the
behavior of individuals when we talk
about collective behavior?
Yeah, I mean this is this question is is
one of the motivations for why I ended
up studying this.
And then I think it ties into like what
I would say is a larger unifying theme
of complex systems in general. Complex
system science, I think if you could
like sum sum it up in one phrase would
be more is different. Mhm.
The whole is greater or different than
the sum of its parts.
Um and that is really evident, I think,
in the study of collective behavior. So,
yeah, I would say that there's something
absolutely different about kind of
blurring your eyes, so to speak, on the
individual components of a system and
treating the system as a thing, as an
emergent thing. And there's a lot of
theories about whether that's like an
epiphenomenal thing, is that just
something that exists on on a
descriptive level, or does this larger
thing, like a flock of birds or school
of fish or a society or an economy, does
it in some way have like causal power
and influence on these like micro-level
individuals? But, I think though the
larger
if the last like whatever 30 years of
complex systems science has shown us
that yes, there is something
qualitatively different about the bigger
picture than just an aggregation of
individual components.
Yeah, I think in terms of, let's say,
socio-cultural groups, the top-down
influence is quite transparent. I mean,
in terms of an economy, the economy that
you function in presumably has a kind of
circular causality with the agents in
the economy. Totally. I'm wondering
whether in terms of more mechanical
complex systems, um, so even in, let's
say, simulation work, is there something
that emerges ontologically in terms of
the actual dynamics of the group as a
whole that can't be reduced to, let's
say, just like a summation of those
individual behaviors?
And I guess
in that, even if there is, can we
distinguish that from top-down
causality? So, as you say, you might
have something which like is
ontologically different. You can
actually say, okay, this is a different
phenomenon.
But, where do you see the top-down
causality coming in before we get to,
let's say, languages or broader cultures
or uh, economies? Yeah, no, that's a
that's a
hotly debated topic, effectively. So,
there's a lot of work that's kind of
trying to actually quantify the amount
of top-down causation that there is. Cuz
of course, like we can always define
some set of macroscopic or
coarse-grained variables from an
ensemble of microscopic variables. Like,
say I have a bunch of particles or a
bunch of gas particles. I can take like
averages like
and come up with quantities like the
temperature or the average mass or the
average velocity. The question is, is
that coarse-grained variable actually
doing anything to that lower level? Does
it feed back down?
And um my intuition is even in
simulation, yes, there is. And then
people have tried to
quantify this. There's people like
Lionel Barnett and Anil Seth at Sussex,
University of Sussex, who have come up
with quantities like dynamical
independence. So, there's an idea where
these coarse-grained variables don't
just act as descriptors or aggregators
of lower-level constituents, but they
end up having their own causal power.
And like intuitively, when you hear
that, it's quite hard to imagine how
that's possible.
Um but it's I think it's one of the most
fascinating and kind of magical things
about complex systems is that basically
these slower like both like spatially
and temporally coarse-grained variables
end up kind of
accumulating a life of their own, and
they can in fact influence and in some
ways be more predictive of the lower
variables
um than just taking the whole like
ensemble of lower variables as
predictors themselves. Um I don't to be
quite frank, although I'm quite
confident that this exists, I don't have
a great intuition for what how that's
possible cuz it kind of flies in the
face of
the last, you know, 200 years of
reductionist science, which is
basically saying that the only causal
direction is up. Everything starts like,
you know, with gluons and quarks, and
then you kind of build the universe up
from there. But all this research is
suggesting that there is some degree of
downward causal influence. And
ontologically, it's actually quite
philosophically difficult to like reckon
with that. I don't I don't know why that
is.
Yes, I mean I wonder whether it's just a
slightly different type of causation
from the kind of gluons or quarks up in
sense that, you know,
going all the way back to Aristotle,
people talk about constraint versus
causation and it might be that just
macro systems constrain the organization
of micro systems. But yeah, it's a
massive question. And yeah, as you said,
it's very philosophically rich. I mean,
strong emergence, weak emergence, all of
this kind of stuff Exactly. Really
philosophical. Excellent. Um going to
sort of humans or or in silico
simulations of humans or cognitive
agents, um
when you put when you sort of run these
in silico simulations, you equip you
know, I read one of your papers and you
equip them with social information,
right? Social priors. So, in one of
yours, you had distance to the net their
neighbors or you would have the rates of
the change of the distance.
I'm wondering whether
would it be possible Do you know, do
individual agents need to be equipped
with these social priors to become
social agents? Mhm. Is there a way that
actually just by acting
and let's say having a shared goal, but
without actual reference to the presence
of other agents,
we have this kind of Gestalt or we have
this kind of emergence of a overall
pattern?
Yeah, definitely. I I think so,
basically, there's different ways you
can effectively introduce correlations
or coupling between agents.
Um the way that we think I mean, there's
a lot of evidence that animals and
agents in society do correlate each
others' activity is through
either directly or indirectly perceiving
aspects of the other. Like we can see
each other. Um schooling fish can sense
their neighbors. Bacteria uh can sense
each other in kind of like all sorts of
uh interesting ways.
But, there's nothing qualitatively
saying that you can't couple
um a a a system of particles with some
like third court-like uh driving or
common source. So, for instance, if I
have a bunch of um particles trying to
navigate towards a food source on some
like media, like they're all attracted
by biochemical gradients towards a food
source, of course, that will induce
correlations in their activity. So, it
will seem like they're all moving as one
where as in fact, there's nothing that's
actually letting them sense each other,
but they're just some kind of common um
source that's giving the appearance of
correlated activity. And this like is a
very uh this is a classic thing that
comes up in neuroscience, too, when
we're looking at large recordings of
neurons.
Often times, we're not recording the
whole brain, right? We're just looking
at some small subsection of neural
activity, and you see all these
correlations between uh neural firing
patterns, and you say, "Oh, look,
they're connected." And people use all
kinds of correlational techniques to
infer the the nature of those
interactions. "Oh, this neuron is
driving that neuron." But, you actually
never know if there's some third um
causal driving force that's actually
responsible for correlated their
activity. And this is actually one of
the nice things about studying
collective animal behavior.
Like in the lab of um Iain Couzin where
I did my PhD, they have the ability to
kind of track with high um resolution a
bunch of individuals, like every
individual in an ensemble in a
collective.
And they can even reconstruct kind of to
some extent the visual fields and the
sensory fields of the individuals in the
group, and in that way, they can kind of
decouple these potentially third
correlating or confounding factors from
the actual use of social information uh
that the individuals might be utilizing.
That's cool. That's interesting. Um
yeah, cuz I can imagine without that, it
can be very confounded. And it makes me
think
to what degree here is uh collective
behavior genuinely advantageous for
these organisms? And I guess it comes to
a kind of evolutionary question.
There is this evolutionary debate about
what, you know, what is the what is the
transmitted thing over epochs? Is it the
actual gene, the species
collective and so on. Exactly.
In some sense, if we just say, "Okay,
well, there are these collect you know,
these aggregations of individuals which
have similar goals and therefore look as
if they are acting in accordance with
one another." And obviously, when you
start recognizing others, well, then you
have to start taking them into account.
Mhm. Your work, have you have you got
any intuition as to whether the presence
of others with shared goals is actually
beneficial for the organism who's
pursuing that individual goal or
whether, you know, it'd be better if we
were all siloed off and
an island onto ourselves? Yeah, yeah,
that's it. That's like a really
perennial question in the study of in
not only collective behavior, but like
sociobiology
kind of in its original formulation by
like E.O. Wilson is, you know, is there
something inherently advantageous to
group living? And
if so, it's clearly not a be-all end-all
cuz we do have the presence of species
that are like solo predators like
wildcats, right? They're they're not
living in herds, but then there's other
animals that are actually living in
groups. And so there's clearly some
trade-off there. So I think
one answer that probably biologists, cuz
I have to admit like I often theorize
very, you know, high-level with concepts
from physics and mathematics, but there
are clear, you know, individual fitness
and more selfish gene-related
motivations for group living. Like a
classic one that has been used to
motivate flocking and schooling fish is
like predation risk. If you're living in
a group, you're basically lowering the
chance that any particular individual
gets predated because and there's also
interesting psychological effects that
flocking has on predators. Like there's
a crowding effect. So if there's a bunch
of individuals in my visual field, it's
harder for me to focus on a single one.
Okay. Okay. So it collectively lowers
the predation risk of everyone in that
collective.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So that's one one
answer to that. There's another
interesting um answer which I I I don't
know this is maybe a little
controversial and I think this is where
it really ties into the free energy
principle.
Which is once you have a collective
system
regardless of whether it's actually
beneficial to the individuals that
partake in it
if the system has dynamics that kind of
allow it to survive
it's kind of created now its own
selection pressure on it in of itself.
So the system um simply by existing and
not dissipating is kind of like
self-evidencing or selecting itself at
perhaps like a higher dynamical scale.
And this is where I think concepts like
the free energy principle which is
really in the game of defining why
things persist in the first place and
what it means to be a thing um has
something to say about about collective
behavior. So I would actually argue that
there's certain
um kind of group dynamics that exist
sometimes even at the expense of
individual fitness. But once you've
entered into this macro scale, the macro
scale is kind of living and trying to
find evidence for its own existence even
if that goes back and punishes uh the
individual actors that actually
originally like cooperated to create it.
Um that's a little bit more
controversial but I think it's a really
good
maybe uh framework for understanding
kind of like maladaptive
group dynamics, things like
misinformation or virality in social
networks, things like that. Well the
Marxists will be screaming that you've
got a great theory there of capitalists,
you know, capitalist realism.
Exactly.
Yeah, that's that's really interesting.
I mean I guess as a you know, with a
more philosophical bent on this, one
thinks, well, where's the kind of locus
of control here?
Because I think intuitively we don't
think that
the group dynamics have control or
agency, like the overall arc of a
culture has the agency of its
constituent individuals. Mhm. But this
idea that there's like Again, I think it
comes down to a kind of constraint
causality distinction. There are certain
things that say that you can do within
capitalist America versus what you could
do in communist Russia. Mhm. And those
actors' constraints without there being
some homunculus. I mean, obviously there
are homunculuses in the in so far as
there are political figures. Mhm. But
No, that's a that's a really interesting
point. I think also what I've been
thinking about is, and this is a even
deeper question, is
and I'm wondering whether you have to
think about this when you talk about
collective behavior and aggregating
individuals. Do you ever think
at what point does one individual end
and what and when does it when how can
we can distinguish one individual from
another? And I know that sounds stupid
because like people will just say, well,
it's the body and and you just have it
you just see them and obviously when we
talk about high-level evolved systems
like the visual system then it probably
is based on, you know,
V1 picking out lines which distinguish
indivi- you know, um individual
organisms. Mhm. But I'm curious in terms
of the actual Bayesian mechanics and the
free energy principle, is there anything
that gives us individuated thingness
beyond taking that as a kind of axiom,
like, oh no, there it just is a thing
that is self-evidencing?
No, yeah, I I don't think it does. I
think that's one of the challenges
of
maybe what the general problem would be
called is like system identification or
Markov blanket identification. How do I
like look at some high-dimensional
system and actually pick out what are
the individuals or the components of
that system? And even within um like bio
biological systems, it's often not
that clear. Like you and me might look
at a
hill of termites or ants colony of ants
and say, "Okay, yeah, those individual
ants are the individuals." But in a
system where they all share the same
genetic material, it becomes a little
bit unclear. And and especially when you
have these kind of self-immolating
sacrifices for the good of the
collective.
It's you start thinking about things
like the extended phenotype. Like are
these individuals actually individuals
or are they kind of just manifestations
of some common gene pool? They're kind
of like the the tools and the fingers
that the gene pool is using to act in
the world.
Um so, I don't think that Bayesian
mechanics has
any like strict definition about
what a thing has to be. I mean, people
will disagree with me on this. Like for
instance, the recent work from um
people like Karl Friston
uh on on particular things, strange kind
of this line of papers, actually makes
particular arguments about what can what
constitutes a thing. And it has to do
with a particular set of dynamical
constraints between the different
subsets of a thing. Like there's active
states and sensory states and there's
certain conditional independence
relations that have have to exist. Um so
so the proposals have been made, but I
don't think anything about Bayesian
mechanics actually tells you how to do
the partitioning of the state space.
It's like given a state space, we can
then start interpreting the dynamics of
that thing
as doing some sort of Bayesian
inference. But where the actual state
space comes from, that's a much deeper
question that I think is like an active
active area of inquiry. That's really
Yeah, that's fascinating. Cuz I guess
one way of doing it would be that you
Well, you act like scientists in some
way and you go, "Well,
if these things are behaving
differently, let's say you got two ants
that are behaving differently, they're
diverging in their movements, then you
would say, 'Well,
we can make the assumption that the
active and sensory states are different.
Their Markov blanket is different.
But if they're replicating one another,
then, you know, that all even that
uh decomposition of the system into
sensory states and active states kind of
kind of informs you to say that that's
one overarching thing. And again, I
mean, I like recruiting kind of a
philosophical vagueness here, which is
that like if I'm a philosophical
perspective, it's probably just an empty
question.
And there is, you know, it's it's well,
what point does a pile of sand become a
heap or, you know, and so on.
And it's it's empty if not if not
interesting and maybe beneficial when
we're talking about
Well, I think there are phenomenological
effects about, you know, to what degree
do I recognize myself as a kind of
siloed off individual versus part of a
group and there are probably very
aberrant ends to that spectrum like
social isolation versus schizophrenia
where I'm kind of melting into the world
versus being completely alone. So, I
think there are and there's a import,
but yeah, I recognize that it's Yeah, I
I do think yeah, I I I totally agree on
a philosophical level and effective
there is no hard line in the sand.
There's not going to be some be-all
end-all definition. Effect like
eventually what will be our deciding
factor is the utility or like I guess
the more pragmatist sort of stances like
the partition we choose for a particular
system, is it going to help us do
something? So, for instance, in a lot of
my um interest in collective animal
behavior, I I've just been mesmerized by
like videos of schooling fish, right?
And these schooling these schools are
not like cells in the sense that
you know, the the I mean, cells
potentially violate this as as well, but
the position and the role that
individuals play within the school are
not fixed, right? So, fish can like go
to different sides of the school.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah,
yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
can kind of act as the eyes and ears of
the school while others are acting more
like the leaders. So, you have like
spontaneous change in roles and
leadership. And that already is
basically telling you that at the higher
level at least
the the kind of sensory states are not
assigned like unchanging individual
identities. So there So already the
partition we use if we want to start
studying the the school as an
individual, that partition has to kind
of supersede individual identity. It has
to be some spatiotemporal coarse
graining of like the movements and
identities of different fish or
particles over time. That's good. Which
partition we use should be a function of
like what question or what hypothesis
we're trying to answer. Yeah. So it
comes down to this teleological or
pragmatic motivation.
Have you got This is a seems like a much
more banal question, but I'm just
curious because I don't know that much
about collective behavior in biology.
Have you got a particular favorite of
collective behavior? You mentioned
schools of fish. Is there anything else
that kind of stands out as impressive?
Yeah, I So schools of fish is probably
my my top one just because they're
visually so mesmerizing. I mean,
starling flocks are are quite
interesting as well. Um particularly
because
so it often happens that in many
realistic schooling scenarios,
although you'll have three-dimensional
schools. This is something I I learned
from my my advisor Ian.
In practice, a lot of the schooling
actually is happening in two dimensions.
So even three-dimensional schools are
actually made up of more like 2D
manifolds. Whereas if you look at
starling flocks, they have very
interesting three-dimensional structure.
Mhm. So you've probably seen these like
um what they call murmurations, like
these kind of shimmering and all they
almost look like chaotic like strange
attractors, the way that they're
folded over on themselves.
And even those have like quasi
two-dimensional structure, but they're
they're those two-dimensional planes are
moving in 3D space. And so stuff like
that is just visually very interesting,
and there's a lot of really interesting
um research like trying to do
high-resolution recording in 3D of all
of the birds in a in a flock and trying
to track them. So, I think that's a
really a beautiful one. But again, it
comes the like it comes back to your
earlier question is what is the actual
function of that? So, sometimes these
murmurations are very beautiful and like
impressive, but people still don't
really know like what the function of
like such crazy displays of collective
coordination are.
Yeah, they bring it brings to mind what
you mentioned about the fact that
they're all There's actually a
conversation I had with Cole because we
were right at the beginning of the first
episode of this podcast. So, we were
talking about well, what is the
imperative?
Cole, you know, originally spoke about
an existential imperative underlying the
free energy principle.
But it's a slightly misleading term
because it doesn't say that, you know,
we have to do anything, right? I could
just
disintegrate right now. It's saying that
if I do persist, then I look as if I am
doing variational Bayesian inferences
and so on. So, I said to myself, well,
but is there an underlying telos to you
know, is there an evolutionary pressure
to survive, right? This is just a
kind of a biological self truth.
And he went, "Yeah." And and you kind of
see that because there are not many
animals that kill themselves, right?
Like there there does seem to be some
underlying pressure or some
self-evidencing survival in a way. Like
survival is self-evidencing.
But it does bring to mind this really
interesting fact that there are some
animals who will self-immolate.
And I'm yeah, I think that is so
interesting.
Is there Is there any kind of idea about
beyond you know, you we mentioned ants
and termites and I think that's kind of
altruism for the group.
Um
Are there any other examples that Well,
I'm wondering if there's any examples
that might just [ __ ] be very tricky to
explain under a kind of Bayesian
mechanics or under an active inference.
I mean, and we can expand that question
more broadly and just say is there any
animal collective behavior that you just
find staggeringly odd under like an
embedded Markov blanket system?
Yeah, I mean, I think like so one of the
the main reasons I went into the
collective motion in particular, like
the schooling fish and the and kind of
flocking birds was because I found them
to be exactly those examples that
violate
the kind of classic image we have of
Markov blankets where you have like kind
of layers of states that are not really
changing. Like you have the particles on
the edge of the blanket and then you
have the ones that are a little more
inside and then finally you have like
the kind of hard nucleus of states.
Yeah. Um so I find that even like basic
collective motion
um kind of evades
uh
proper understanding under the current
iterations of Bayesian mechanics. I
mean, this is part of the reason the
paper you mentioned that kind of studies
uh
like frames individual elements of like
a school as like active inference
agents. Mhm. That that paper actually
didn't try to formulate the whole school
as a collective. That was one of the
other objectives I had during my PhD and
it's something I'd still like to to
study if I have time. But um I found
that actually doing proper Bayesian
mechanics on the whole school as if the
school is the unit of analysis was quite
difficult precisely because collective
motion is an example where the roles
that individuals play um is changing
dynamically. So if we are to find like a
stable Markov blanket description that
satisfies all the tenets of the free
energy principle, we will have to kind
of come up with a more dynamic um
version of system identification that
allows you to kind of uh dynamically
redraw who is a sensory state, what
parts of your high-dimensional state
space are playing the role of active
versus sensory versus internal
dynamically over time. So I think even
like the most kind of basic examples,
ant colonies as well, right? They're
dynamic mixing system, although the
roles are more genetically predetermined
for the social insects.
Though all these examples I think are
are
a bit of a challenge to the classic
formulation of Bayesian mechanics.
Um
Right. Yeah. Well, I guess one of the
earlier critiques of active inference
was that it's a kind of state-based
um sys- you know, formalism, hm, which
doesn't allow for kind of dynamic change
as you say and over time-ness.
And
I recognize I think this is something
that actually came up in a old Twitter
discussion between Maxwell and Kate Nave
about uh
path integrals and the path dynamics. It
might be you know, you're right at the
forefront of this research. Maybe it's
worth just for the audience unpicking
what is the difference between the kind
of state-based or static active
inference versus a path-based
uh active inference which allows for
this kind of
well, I you know, think of
metamorphosizing Markov blankets or
something like that.
Yeah. Yeah, for sure. So, the the
classic um variant of
deriving the free energy principle
rests on specifying like a what's called
a steady state distribution. So, it's
actually just a probability distribution
over the states of the system that
should not change.
Um and this is you know, this it can
generally be applied to many systems at
least on some time scale. Like so, it
seems like the distribution of particles
in a rock or in me and you for example
doesn't seem to change on quite so long
of a time scale. Of course, the rub is
in how do I define what a state is? Is a
state a
particular cell cuz cells are turning
over all the time or is it maybe a
tissue, things like that? But anyway,
the the basic um free energy principle
as it was
I mean, I I guess as it was
pedagogically described. This is I'm
referring to papers like the free energy
principle for a particular physics, the
monograph from 2019.
So,
the idea is you you have this stationary
distribution over states
and and it's a
like very trivially a multivariate
system. So, there's a potential for some
of those states to be active states,
sensory states, internal states. You've
kind of partitioned the system, but
what's important is that over long
times, if I measure the system, the
probability distribution of being in
this part of state space or this part of
state space, that probability is fixed.
It doesn't change over time. So, it
still allows for particles to move
around
if I look at the individual
trajectories. Like
things can change, there can be
fluctuations, but the stationary
density, the probabilities are are
constant. Yeah.
That's in contrast with the more recent
path integral or path formulation, where
it's not the distribution over
um the states themselves, like finding
my position in this part of the room at
over time on average, but it's more a
probability distribution over paths or
trajectories themselves.
So, the point of this is that
um
there's also a stationary measure or a
stationary distribution, but it's not
over particular points in state space,
but it's rather over sequences of
points. Yeah.
Yeah. And that allows you to have a lot
more flexibility in the dynamics, where
you can have things that appear
non-stationary
in the sense of if I look at just the
positions of the variables, that will be
changing over time, but it's because
there's actually a more like abstract
stationary measure, which is operating
on the paths or the sequences of
variables of the system.
Um so, yeah, this is what I allows
I I mean, apparently, this is I think
what's going to be upcoming as we see
this formulation unpacked more,
especially in terms of simulations,
we're going to see versions of this
Bayesian mechanics applied to systems
that are moving in time and not
stationary. And this is only something
you can get with the path-based
formulation.
So, when you talk about the states,
so are we talking about the sort of
path that states take or the kind of
position that they have at a given time.
Mhm. What part of the Markov blanket are
we talking here? Because some people
talk about the internal states,
uh you know, parameter sizing beliefs
over external states and their
self-evidencing. Mhm. And then some
people talk about the actual blanket
states
or the particular or or some people talk
about blanket states reducing VFE or
some people talk about the particular
states, which is the blanket states plus
the internal states. So, when we're
talking about states
uh tending towards an attracting set.
What what what what are the commitments
that we're making here in terms of which
states those are?
So, yeah, people will disagree on this.
I mean, in the original formulation of
the free energy principle, it should be
all of those things. So, blanket,
sensory, active, and internal all have a
stationary distribution defined over
them. Right. So, so it's basically the
joint distribution of all the subsets of
states. That's the thing that should be
unchanging. Is that including Would that
include the external states or we're
allowing those to have some
non-ma- you know, chaotic element to
them? Yeah, I mean, for the mathematics
in the original formulation to work, you
actually also need the external states
to be unchanging, which is one of the
critiques that the free energy principle
had got is like
you're not really defining a stationary
system to be the system per se, like the
agent, but you're actually including the
whole world Yeah, yeah, yeah. your agent
is embedded in as part of your
stationary measure. And you know, you
could make arguments that oh well, it's
um you know, referring to just the eco
niche, like the behaviorally relevant
part of the agent's world that it's
trying to control. So, it's kind of like
the agent is forcing its external states
to to obey the stationary measure. Um
but I think the path-based formulation
allows you to get around that cuz all
these things now become non-stationary
if considered in terms of just raw
states.
But but yeah, it originally it does
include all all the subsets of states.
But it sounds like even when we're
talking about the change of
the path of states, there still seems to
be some kind of predetermined
characteristics or predetermined
attracting set. So that path is tending
towards a certain probability. For sure.
So you allow for some what Carl would
call sort of itinerancy or, you know,
some deviation from that ideal, but
you've still got some pre-characteristic
dynamics. I'm just wondering, you know,
you'll know a lot more about physics
than I do. How much does that really
square with kind of fundamental physics
or understanding of the world? Like is
it is it actually feasible to say
even if we allow for some itinerancy and
change over time, there are there's like
a mathematical way that you could still
describe that?
Yeah, I I think it that actually that
assumption is quite consistent with
physics cuz
I mean, there there's a lot of like
equivalency between these different
things. So as soon as I say, "Oh, these
stochastic
differential equations tend toward some
attracting set." Mhm.
Another way of saying that is I've just
written down a particular form of their
flow, like the way that they change over
time, some particular equations of
motion. Yeah. And if those equations of
motion meet a few basic constraints,
like one of them is that they don't
diverge infinite into positive or
negative infinity, which is like I think
a a pretty safe assumption. I mean, if
we if we're assuming all of our
equations diverges to infinity, we
wouldn't be able to do much with them.
So as long as you say that this equation
doesn't diverge to infinity,
another way of saying that is there is
some measure that this belongs to. It
basically will tend towards something
with constant probabilities. And those
constant probabilities in in certain
systems will be better described in
terms of paths rather than states. So
like the paths of the system will have
constant probability. So although that
sounds like restricting, it's actually
it's actually just a a statement of
writing down any differential equation
that doesn't have some crazy like kind
of impossible form. Right.
Okay.
Final question on the physics because
you did a reply to this how particular
is the physics of the free energy
principle by Aguilera and colleagues.
And
I just was really curious cuz it it it's
very much pertains to what I was saying
about what states are we talking about
the particular states, the internal
states, or blanket states. And you say
in that paper and I can quote, "I
express general agreement with the
target article's statement that the
marginal flow of internal states does
not point along variational free energy
gradients evaluated at the most likely
internal state. However, in this
commentary I focus on the flow of
particular states in turn brackets
internal and blanket states and their
variational free energy gradients and
the average flow of these systems do
point along variational free energy
gradients." And in my notes I've
literally just written, "What does this
mean?"
Yeah, no, thanks for bringing that up
because that I I wrote another
commentary, I think, on the same article
that was a lot more like it was more
about the sparse coupling conjecture and
that one actually didn't get much
attention. But so yeah, that effectively
this is a very interesting point cuz
the the one of the main hypotheses of
the free energy principle and this
manifests in terms of like particular
process theories like predictive coding
is that if you look at the internal
states of some system,
they are pointing directly towards the
free energy minimum. So either on
average or if it's a deterministic for a
particular path, the system looks like
it's minimizing free energy very nicely.
So in the same way we train deep neural
networks to exactly maximize the ability
to predict the test data, we train
predictive coding networks to exactly
minimize free energy. So they're taking
like the direction of steepest descent
towards the free energy minimum and at
that minimum is where your inference is
best. At the local minimum of the free
energy, your inference over external
states is the best it can be given your
approximate posterior and your
generative model. So, what Aguilera et
al.'s um paper found is that if you look
at like
very simple stochastic differential
equations, these are like uh in this
class of linear systems, so they're very
easy to analyze.
And they're probably not the best model
of the more complex systems we're
actually interested in in biology, but
they're a really good starting point.
What they found is that Sorry, is that
That's where I live. Yeah.
Truck outside, yeah.
All right. Um
Uh that they found that even for these
simple linear systems, the average
internal states are actually not
pointing towards these free energy
minimum. And that was kind of posed as
like a challenge to the free energy
principle. And the the mathematics
behind that derivation, in my opinion,
were uh totally sound. So, it is true
that actually even in these uh
very simple linear diffusion systems,
you don't get this kind of nice
interpretation as internal states
walking in the steepest direction
towards the best inference. They're
actually taking a more circuitous route
towards the minimum, which entails the
best inference. However, if you
extend your um
your kind of your your
definition of internal states to include
also the active states and the sensory
states, so the part so-called particular
states, the things that differentiate
the particle from the external
environment, then those things actually
are pointing down free energy gradients.
And this it kind of is in line with this
general
idea that I think is a lot more in line
with like the idea of sensory-motor
coupling. It's not just the internal
states that are doing inference, but the
internal states are kind of cooperating
or conspiring with your active states in
order to collaboratively get to that
free energy minimum, at which point
inference is exact or as exact as it can
be given your approximations. So, it's
saying, "Okay, I don't need to go the
the steepest way to
the free energy minimum. I can take like
a kind of curvy circuitous route, but
I'm at the same time I'm pushing my
active and sensory states in such a way
that will actually minimize the time it
takes us to get to the free energy
minimum." And that was kind of the point
of that um
of that article or one of the points.
No, that's really useful. I'm just
wondering um so, when we talk about
so, we're talking here about the sort of
self-evidence thing or the gradient
descent of particular state.
Should we
is could we say that actually it might
What would it mean Okay, what would it
mean to say What would it mean What
would it look like if I said, "We're
doing gradient descent just on blanket
states?"
So, let's ignore silo off the internal
states for a second and just say, "Are
blanket states
absent the internal states also Do they
also point down uh variational free
energy gradients?" Yeah, I don't think
that is guaranteed actually. I don't
think blanket states are are necessarily
pointing down um free energy gradients
necessarily without taking into account
sensory and uh or sorry uh internal
states. So, the internal states are kind
of the things that are driving the
active states to jointly minimize the
free energy. And the free energy recall
is defined on both the blanket and the
internal states cuz it's defined on the
observations, which are like the blanket
states. And it's also defined on your
beliefs over external states, which in
this case are parameterized by internal
states. So, if you define the the free
energy just on the blanket states, I
don't think it's guaranteed to it will
be minimized in the long run, but it's
not guaranteed that the dynamics are
pointing in the direction of steepest
descent.
Well, how do you when people So,
I think people This is kind of coming to
the kind of education of active
inference, I guess, and and part of this
podcast is
me learning and the audience learning
alongside with me. When people when
people like you talk about internal
states,
I understand what it means to sort of
parameterize beliefs over external
states, and
in some ways you're doing VFE because
you want to return to like a set of
external states which is viable for your
existence. So, fish are not going to be
found outside water, or I'm not going to
be found in an ice cube, so I want my
ice cube freezer, I don't know.
Um
Now, my sort of a persistent question
that I've always had, and I don't think
anyone has really answered, and I'm not
sure there is an answer, is
is that we say that the internal states
are kind of the vehicle for these
beliefs.
But, are they Could you also just say
they are these beliefs? Like, is there
anything over and above the internal
states beyond these Bayesian beliefs?
Yeah, no, that's a really good question.
So, this is this this gets into a a
bigger question also about
identifiability and uniqueness of the
free energy principle and Bayesian
mechanics. So,
base In short, the the internal states
are not just simply the beliefs
because they are whatever physically
they are. Like, if if we're looking at a
school of fish and we're saying, "These
five fish are playing the role of the
internal states." Or, looking at a cell,
this part of DNA is is playing the role
of the internal states. It's encoding
the the
um production of proteins. That itself
that internal state doesn't have
anything intrinsically
it's not parameterizing parameters of
probability distributions over external
states. So, what's always
at play when you're saying that the
internal states are about, or some in
somehow, uh representing external
states, is there's always a function
there which in the classic free energy
literature is called the synchronization
map. And what this is is it's a function
that takes your internal states and it
maps them into the parameters of
probability distributions. So if I want
to it's basically something that takes
the raw like dirty physics of the
system, however it is. It's like
you know, the metals and the ions and
the the the things that actually consist
of your system and it's mapping them
into a space of probability
distribution. So if we wanted to say
that um my neurons are encoding beliefs
about the position of objects in the
room, what that that function, that
synchronization map would be doing is it
would like take the firing rate of a
neuron, which is like an actual physical
neurophysiological property that I can
measure from the neuron, and it's
mapping it to something like the mean of
a Gaussian distribution or the variance
of a Gaussian distribution. So
it I mean, I guess in that sense it's
like
do you think that the firing rates of
the neurons simply are the belief? I
would say that
and actually this this kind of hints at
at something I I um saw you talking
about Alex Kiefer on on one of your
earlier podcasts. It's like this kind of
identity problem. Like are the neural
firing rates the belief, the
representation themselves, or is there
some map that takes the raw physics of
the system and then maps it into a
probability distribution, into a
representation? So I think you always do
need that function that actually takes
the system and maps it to a belief. But
the problem with identifiability is it
seems like there may be many candidate
functions that take the the system
states and map them to a probability
distribution over beliefs. So it's a
very hard to just look at a system and
say, "Oh yeah, it's forming beliefs
about like the average distance to
neighbors or the the light refraction in
the room or the contrast of some some
image out there." We we usually come to
the table with very strong priors about
for instance neural coding. We think
that neurons either code things with the
timing of spikes or they use like the
firing rate. And that's how they do the
encoding. And that's basically saying we
come to the table with priors about what
that function is. But in theory, there's
nothing about the free energy principle
that tells you what that function is.
So, it's a very hard like
identifiability problem in general.
Okay, that's that's that's interesting.
Yeah, I mean
another thing that kind of sticks in my
mind when I think about this is
where does the where did like
where do the beliefs stop? So, what
point is something internal to the
system and what point is something
external to the system?
So,
um
like for example, let's say my eye,
right? There's something like me, let's
take as a kind of presupposition. I am
conducting variational Bayesian
inference might like over the external
states, but the external states in some
strange way are also myself. Right?
Because they're also, let's say, the
observations that come with respect to
my glucose levels. Now, that's because I
need to have some beliefs by some uh
probability distribution that my glucose
levels are going to tend towards a
certain point. In that like there is
some internal belief about an external
state, but that external state is
actually still within me. I get we get
we kind of get around this through this
notion of embedded Markov blankets,
right? Like I'm not actually
parameterizing those beliefs, but
actually my cells are. But I guess the
point here is
is it is are we and it comes back to a
question that I've had loads of times
and people have had different answers to
it. Is this just a useful structuring
tool here where I can just say, well,
I don't really know why or how or when
this Markov blanket ends and becomes
part of a bigger order Markov blanket
and so on until you get something that
that's like to be me,
but it's useful. And we can do some
useful math or useful physics based on
it. Because I just think like again,
it's philosophically vague as to does it
make sense like is the cell is it part
of the you know,
Is there just a straight elision really
between an internal state and an
external state from the perspective of a
cell? Because it seems that it's also
doing Bayesian beliefs on its own
location. Yeah. It's own status. It's
own right? Like So
I've always struggled with that with the
free energy principle. Yeah, it makes
sense for me that the internal states I
have to be parameterizing beliefs about
where I am in the world or who I'm with
and so on. But what about like
what about myself? I've got to be about
my glucose levels, my temperature, my
well-being and all the way down to my
like very granular physics level. Yeah.
Like where does it stop? Yeah, exactly.
I I think the generic answer to this I
think is basically what you meant by
embedded Markov blankets which is
if I if I look at like a coarse-grained
level, like more psychological level of
explanation. Like you you have beliefs
about who's in the other room or what's
behind your door.
So that itself could be drawn out as
like a Bayesian network where you have
some sensory states which are like your
sensory organs like your eyes and ears
and nose.
And then you have your internal state
which is like your psychological state
or something or some coarse-grained
representation of what your brain is
thinking. And then you have that
external state which is like the
presence or absence of another person.
Each of those nodes in our Bayesian
graph we can kind of double click on and
like
zoom in and that itself is a
a thing that has internal blanket
sensory. So that's like the generic
answer that that people like Karl
Friston will talk about with the
renormalization group. Like you have
Markov blankets at different scales and
of course the work of Maxwell Ramstead
and people like that who are
literally like writing papers about how
exactly this happens. You have this
nested Markov blanket. So I think that
is the the general answer is that
every time we write down a Bayesian
network and a graph we're like saying,
"Okay, that's the blankets. That's the
internal. That's the external." Every
time we do that, we're kind of
admitting, "Well, actually, I can always
like take what I consider a single state
and just rip it up and like start
partitioning that." Right.
And then I think the the ultimate
conclusion of that exercise is basically
your conclusion, which is it all becomes
a matter of why are we doing this? Like,
why am why am I at this level of
zoomed-outness?
And it's probably for some practical
utility as a modeller, as a
neuroscientist, as a physicist.
Yeah. Yeah. So, if we take the sort of
psychological perspective, and let's
say, you know, so let's say you actually
will use your uh preprint. So, the paper
that I was mentioning before was from
the um
I believe it's collective behavior from
surprise minimization. So, that's a
really great preprint that people can
check out. It's obviously quite
technical, but there's again lots of
things that people can get out of it.
Um
let's say, you know, we embed these
we're doing these um
Bayesian beliefs over the distance that
I am from another person and the rate of
change of that distance.
I guess my question here is
am I also conducting Bayesian beliefs
about where I am?
Do I get where I am out of
just like
do I get where I am just out of the
beliefs about where other people are?
Even at this very psychological level,
you know, there's someone else in the
other room. Do I also need to be doing
Bayesian beliefs about myself in
relation to those external world? And it
does that mean that I am also in some
ways like I've got a dual perspective.
I've got like dual monism I am doing the
Bayesian belief about myself as if I was
part of the external world. Yeah, kind
of like doing doing theory of mind on
your own self. Like having to simulate
your own inference process. Yeah, I
mean, so I think the argument made in
that collective behavior from surprise
minimization paper
is that um you can get away without
that. Very Like you can get away with a
lot of coordinated behavior
where agents are tuning their own
position and their velocity in space
just by operating on very low-level
reflex arcs. Basically just trying to
minimize sensory prediction error. And
so those agents in that paper don't have
any representation of their own
position. That's not like a latent
variable in their generative model. All
they do is they have some velocity
vector and that induces prediction
errors. And what they can do is they can
just change that velocity to basically
reduce prediction errors. So you can get
a get quite a lot of sophisticated
behavior without that representation.
However, I think there are
plenty of good examples of systems and
maybe this gets more into like what you
would call metacognition, although it
doesn't even have to be that. Yeah,
yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
But there are systems where you would
like to have
a representation of a random variable in
your system that represents something
like the self position.
Um and and you would like to do
inference over that variable. And that
basically is what active inference is.
If I have a a variable that corresponds
to some latent that can control my own
body position or my speech or whatever.
And doing inference over that latent
variable is basically what ends up being
some kind of agency or control. Um and I
think the reason the cases when you
would want to have that extra variable
are ones where the dynamics of yourself
are are above and beyond what can just
be determined from your sensory inputs.
So for like these reflexive fish, I can
get away without having a self variable
because their behavior is pretty much
completely a deterministic function of
their sensory states.
There is a little bit of like memory in
there because they have the belief from
the last time step of belief updating,
but it's very simple. It's not like a
very complex de- dependency. When you
have individual um agents that have a
lot of like autonomy, I guess, which I
would just parse into like more
long-term non-linear dynamics, then it
makes sense to introduce another latent
variable in your model that corresponds
to something like myself or my position
or my actions. And at that point, you're
going to get more of like a I would say
a a tension between externally driven um
behaviors that are driven by sensory
stimuli only and internal more like
endogenous or autonomous behaviors.
Yeah.
those are the cases when you would want
to put that latent variable in there.
Yeah, I've been I've been thinking about
this myself. I'm we're just finishing up
these edits for this flow states paper
and um trying to explain sort of with
Lars and Carl and and others and trying
to explain
sort of what it means for this you know,
this is the self is the so-called sort
of hidden like one of just many hidden
causes according to active inferences as
a hypothesized latent cause.
And trying to explain kind of the
difference between an internal cause and
an external cause for something that's
already presumably internal, right? Like
me.
And um
Yeah. Totally. This is cool though. It's
uh yeah. Yeah. I I think I remember
hearing maybe you you're probably more
up-to-date with this, but I remember
hearing Carl talk about like
the idea that the the very fact that we
introduced something like a self was
basically a new structure in the
generative model Mhm. um in order to
explain disparate inputs. So, it's like
I'm I'm hearing a bunch of speech
signals
and if I don't if I only have one latent
variable in my model, which is like
there is somebody speaking, Right.
then it's not going to be a good enough
model of like the speech signals. And
when you get enough of these like social
signals, it actually becomes the free
energy minimizing solution to break that
node into two. And there's one that I
can control and there's one that's
someone else that I can't control.
Exactly.
the best way to like explain the data.
Well, yeah, and presumably this is
happening actually in developmental
psychology and developmental biology
whereby a child doesn't really know have
a self-other distinction. Mhm.
And I I always relate it back to I think
action is very important. So, this is
going back to the work of someone like
Chris Frith and uh the comparator model,
whereby I can make predictions about the
consequences of my action. And the very
fact that I can do that and witness the
sensory outcomes of my action means I
kind of get what I get the sensory motor
arc. And therefore, I can have a
higher-order uh inference that there is
something that that internal to my
generative model that is driving that
action. I guess the question here is
what's happening in something like a
psychopathology, like thought insertion
in schizophrenia, where people don't
trust that the thoughts that I mean, I
think this is actually kind of true. And
I think the Buddhists actually fleshed
it out quite well that obviously if you
actually meditate, you'll see that well,
the thoughts are not yours. Like they're
not cut They're not You're not making
the thoughts. But there's a classic
thing in schizophrenia of like
people who are schizophrenic will often
think that the thoughts that they're
thinking aren't theirs. Mhm. They're
being beamed in by an alien or
government surveillance operation. And
how you feed in something like a
predictive model into that unless you
take thought as an action and then say,
"Well, I'm predicting the outcomes of my
thought." and so on. That becomes tricky
because I guess we think of predictions
as thoughts in some realist way. And so,
you end up with this circular loop. But
yeah, it's um Fascinating. Yeah. I think
it's Yeah, it is fascinating. I think
it's a I think it's a I think this idea
of the self as an inferred cause is
reasonable. I think the only problem is
is that it engenders some kind of
potential homunculus.
Mhm. Which is So, well, well, what's
doing the inference in the first place?
Yeah, exactly. Um but these are these
are questions for a
Yeah, that brings you back to having to
define internal states. Like what if the
internal states are the self and you're
inferring that that's even exists?
You need to define the inference process
on some other subset of states. Right.
How do you get off ground in the first
place? Yeah, exactly. Yeah. Cool. Uh
well, you've just given me another paper
idea. And maybe a PhD idea.
So, okay, awesome. I wanted to ask about
the scene construction paper cuz I've
been really interested in scene
construction and I was I was happy you
know I I saw you work with Betancourt
and I think his work is really amazing.
Uh, and that I I just wrote a paper on
attention and it's super inspired by
what he was doing with Carl and this
especially their selective attention
paper, their 2019 paper. Yeah,
definitely. Yeah. Maybe just for the
audience who aren't who probably idea
and intuition what scene construction
is. Mhm. And they probably think of it
as visual although I really like the
sort of language example here. Yeah,
yeah. You could explain just a bit at
various or high level what scene
construction is.
Yeah, no, I like that you brought up the
language example cuz that's that's
actually what originally compelled me.
Even when I saw those papers on scene
construction, I actually immediately
thought of it in terms of like parsing
and language. Mhm. A scene construction
is just kind of a a type of hidden
variable inference. So, I have a bunch
of sparsely sampled data points.
And then given that sequence of data
points, like little sensory samples, I
suddenly kind of
infer something that's explaining all of
them at once. Like, oh, this this is the
latent cause. This is the latent exp-
explanation that kind of unifies all
these disparate um,
these disparate data points. And I guess
the construction aspect comes from two
ways.
One is the fact that usually the way we
get that sequence of sparse data is
through some kind of sampling. So, like
as I read a sentence,
I I'm typ- in in like Western languages
you're typically reading left to right.
As my eyes go right across the page, I'm
gathering more evidence
and I'm constructing the scene as in my
posterior probability distribution over
these different explanations is kind of
shifting until at some point and often
we see with human language and visual
understanding, there's kind of this like
non-linear feedback where oh, it it kind
of snaps into place. Oh, this is what's
going on. And it's very interesting
seeing this in language too, like in
different languages like German for
instance, the verb will come at the end
of the sentence. So, you kind of have to
wait until the end of the sentence
before that meaning kind of snaps into
place.
So, that that's generally what I would
describe as scene construction. And then
in the visual case, often it's
you might be looking at a
painting or something, like an ambiguous
painting. Let's say some a modernist
maybe abstract thing with not very clear
figures. And you're sparsely sampling it
with your eyes trying to figure out like
what what's actually going on here. And
at some point when sampling you you get
that Gestalt impression of oh, there's
like a figure in a cloak or something.
And that that moment of Gestalt
recognition is like the the act of
constructing the scene, of inferring the
latent explanation for all the sensory
data that I've
that I've gathered.
Excellent. That's really useful. I guess
something that Beck's work really drove
home to me and impelled me to write this
paper was the importance of context.
So, if you're doing a sort of Yarbus
task,
where you have a picture you exactly
what you just said, you have a picture
and then someone says, "Well, how rich
are the family in this picture?" And
then you scan all of the furniture and
you look at the clothes and then they
they ask something else like I don't
know I I don't actually know what it is,
but you know, let's say, "How well do
they get along with each other?" And you
look at how they're sitting and you look
at whether they're looking at each
other.
So, context is clearly driving a kind of
overall
uh the the the kind of derivation of a
latent cause in some ways because you're
going, "Okay, well, I'm going to pick
out this evidence and that's going to
drive my inference." So, are we Would
you say that we're always integrating a
kind of higher-order context
when we're doing scene construction such
that
you know, there is no such thing as the
kind of neutral scene. Um it's always
you know, the inference is always being
driven by our recognition of where we
are, what we are, and so on.
Totally. Yeah, I think that's that that
that's one of the most interesting
aspects of
Bayesian modeling in general is like
the the the ability for people to very
rapidly infer a context, which in in to
map it back to the the kind of
abstraction I used to describe scene
construction at the beginning is like
you're inferring which latent
explanations you're even testing. Yeah,
exactly.
case of what um do you get the sense
that the family in the in the painting
is rich? You're suddenly
that's inference of a rapid context that
then induces which latent explanations
am I interested in learning about, like
rich versus not rich. Whereas if it if
the um the cue or the prompt was
is the man wearing a red shirt? Then the
different latent explanations that
you've suddenly inferred you have to
test is a different set. Yeah, yeah,
yeah.
that's like one of the most amazing and
and kind of under-explored
abilities that humans and other animals
have is they can infer
they can use context to basically
quickly infer a generative model. So
like the context kind of selects the
generative model that then you use to do
something like active inference.
Yeah.
Well, I've been I've been thinking about
this um
because clearly
clearly it's it's just not
computationally feasible to contemplate
or assess every possible state, right? I
mean this is the whole
basis of variational Bayesian inference
is that
Yeah, exactly. kind of key of why is
just it's in almost infinitely diverse
in its state space. Exactly.
I've been kind of proposing that there's
a high-order action policy which does
the kind of pruning um to use kind of
reinforcement language, the kind of
pruning of your potential state space.
And I've been thinking about that a lot
in terms of action because even action,
right? You can't I don't consider doing
absolutely everything at any given time.
Have you got any other like further
intuitions about how that might work?
Because I think the slight the slight
tricky thing here is that
we have a kind of higher order
policy, let's say, to prune our state
space, but that needs itself to be
driven by observation.
Right? I need to know, okay, I'm going
to prune accordingly because I've
observed something in the world, right?
Like so I see that it's raining, for
example, in London right now, and so
like I'm just immediately pruning
swimming trunks and sunglasses and so
on. But I need to do that observation in
the first place. So it sounds like I've
got to have the higher order action
policy to observe the world to drive my
context. I'm just curious about how much
how how deeply recursive does that go?
Yeah, I I think like the the overall
my I mean
the I would like to think that there's a
generic solution where you basically can
start with no structure and like build
everything from scratch, but I think
there's basically no free lunch here.
Even and I agree with you that like the
maybe the best way to explain human
behavior is that you're inferring a
context or inferring um something that
then allows you to prune or select a
model that then you can use in practice.
But the process by which you do that
also assumes some kind of model. Like
what's the model by which you infer I
need to act to do this?
Where do those models come from? These
like deep hyper priors about the spaces
of models that I can select at at like a
lower level?
Those are probably things that are
developmentally inborn. Those are That's
probably the space that like evolution
actually works on. Like on the space of
kind of hyper priors or deep hyper
models that like babies are born with in
their brain. And these things are are
probably things that you and I couldn't
elucidate in like
like
in in human cognitive neurosciences like
a probability of the dots moving right
versus left. Like that's a likelihood we
can write down. These kinds of models
that are like the models about how do I
select which structures to use for a
given task? Those are probably very hard
to put into words, but those are the
sorts of things that I expect
developmental psychologists have
somewhat of a hold on. Like these they
probably have to do with like intuitive
folk physics, like things like
there there are objects, there are
agents, there are things with like
spatio-temporal correlations over time,
like very deep physical constructs.
But um but I do I do think that at a
more mechanistic level what you're
saying makes a lot of sense. I think
like one way you could formulate this is
in terms of mixture models. So
mixture models is like I have some
assignment variable that's very high up
that tells me which model
am I using right now?
And so the mixing variable is what you
infer. Mhm. And then given the inference
of the mixing variable that effectively
selects one of five or 10 or 1,000
different alternative explanations for
the data.
And usually those are form are are
models of the same form, like a Gaussian
mixture model is a mixture of Gaussians.
Mhm. But I think in what you're
discussing, what you're mixing are like
totally alternative structures. Like one
structure that I'm inferring, one
context I'm inferring I'm in is like I'm
driving a race car. Another context is
that I'm talking to a friend or a
colleague. And those are totally
different models. Um I think one place
where the mixture model falls apart is
with mixture models you would assume
that when you infer that higher level
assignment, sometimes that inference can
kind of be wide. So you're not sure in
what context you're in.
But when you look at human behavior,
people tend not to mix context. There's
probably some experimental paradigms
where you get that, but often times
people infer like they kind of select
like I'm definitely going to make these
assumptions going forward, I'm
definitely going to make these.
So there might be something like a
better model of structure selection than
mixture models. But that would be one
idea I think like mathematically where
to get started would to be looking at
like mixtures of structures effectively.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. Nice. I I spoke to
Sanjeev Namjoshi about this on the
podcast who's at Versus with you and the
yesterday I spoke to him about it and we
went back and forth and I think we ended
up grounding it out in evolution. So I
think you're absolutely You're
absolutely right. I think
there are a couple of things I want to
say to that. One is it's always I tell
everyone this on this podcast and
personally that I think it's always a
bit dangerous to just take one slice of
the generative model at one slice of
time and take that to be what actually
happening. It's always dynamic. The
observations are always feeding into the
upper levels which are feeding back down
and I guess that's the beauty of a kind
of
predictive coding or a deep parametric
modeling system is that like this is
just an idealization. It's it's it's
constantly happening. Yeah, personally.
Um I think the other like point of
uh complexity here is that not only uh
do we need to let's say derive a
context, we also have to derive the
salience of a context or like the
relevance of a context. So, you know,
I've been Yeah, I wrote this paper where
I'm kind of talking about the circular
causality between preferences and the
tension. Mhm. And
something that I kind of realized was
well
well, I knew it obviously because it's
just from my life that if I'm hungry,
like if I'm truly starving, I'm not
going to I don't care about anything
else that's on like that seems
fundamentally peripheral at time whether
that's finishing a paper or, you know,
being on my phone and and so on. Which
means that like there's almost not only
is there a higher order policy that I
prune my state space according to the
fact that I'm now hungry, but also that
now trumps any other states possible
state space like I'm on my phone or I'm
writing my essay. Which implies that
there's like an even higher level
precision weighting policy that says
well, not only do you have to prune
accordingly, but you also have to prune
in the hierarchical fashion. Yeah. And
I don't know again, I don't know how
deep this goes cuz as Carl will tell us
anatomically the brain is very ridgy and
very recursive.
Yeah, that's true. No, that I mean that
also reminds me I think of this paper of
Burke's that you mentioned from 2019,
right? Cuz if I remember correctly, that
version of selective attention actually
depended on the preferences. Is that
right? So yeah, that that's something
like other than other than that work by
Burke and I guess the paper you're
discussing now, I don't know of much
work that explicitly uses the
preferences
to then select what generative model is
being used for inference. Cuz you're
absolutely right, it's not just oh, I
have some observations that I infer the
context, which then tells me how to act,
but that inference also depends on like
what your goals are, like what is
important right now. And usually we get
importance in the kind of classic
model-based reinforcement learning ways,
we we roll out a given policy and we see
how much does that policy overlap with
what I want. Like a reward function. We
basically evaluate policies in terms of
reward functions. But what you're
suggesting
maybe cannot be accommodated in that
way, where the actual inference itself
is biased by
it's not just policy selection, but even
state selection or state inference is
biased by what's important, what's
relevant.
Um and I think you there are ways you
can get that, like there's this um
generalized free energy paper by Thomas
Parr and Karl Friston from 2019,
where they show that in that in that
particular formulation of variational
free energy called the generalized free
energy, you actually do get this
interesting influence on state inference
from preferences. So your preferences
will kind of optimistically bias your
state inference so that you'll only be
doing inference about things that kind
of matter for your action selection. So
that might be one one place to also Carl
will point me in the direction of that
paper cuz you read it. You read my paper
and then obviously
tell me about this one. That sounds
absolutely right. Yeah, because I mean
my way of coming at it was thinking,
well,
in principle, you know, there's near
infinite things that I can optimize my
free energy minimization over, right?
Like
I could and there are ways out of this.
I mean, some people will talk about
something like, uh,
you know, Julian Kiverstein or Mark
Miller or Mark Anderson was all about
aerodynamics. So, it's not enough just
to minimize free energy. There needs to
be a constantly improving slope of
prediction error minimization. Mhm. But,
I still don't think that does it because
in principle,
uh, I could just get way better at
tidying my room. But, like that's just
or or something extremely trivial. Yeah.
That's not going to cut it ultimately
because I might just end up starving.
So,
it's Yeah, it is exactly as you said.
Um,
I I still think this can be couched in
terms of something like an expected free
energy function. It's just It's just far
It's just higher order. Yeah.
trickles down from it. So, it's that as
you say, like
now we have like a selective generative
model. In truth, I haven't thought too
much about how this could be implemented
mathematically Yeah.
you know, That's the place that that cuz
that is Yeah, that's totally true. You
could actually say
cuz cuz the typical way we do the
expected free energy is in like this
brute force enumeration. Like, let's say
I did this. I did X versus Y. If I did
X, what would my expected free energy
look like? It would be a combination of
the utility, which is like the
preferences, and then this info
information gain. Mhm. If you were to
evaluate that brute force for like model
selection, like if I was to select this
model and then go through a whole round
of active inference with this model, it
just becomes very hard to compute the
expected free energy, I think. So, maybe
there's just a better algorithm or
implementation that would allow you to
kind of heuristically
evaluate these counterfactual
consequences. Like, if I selected this
model, what would my what would that
make me less hungry? Would that like
save me? Right. But, you probably have
to have come up with some heuristic or
some clever way to to get around the
enumeration. Well, I wonder whether it
could just be belief-free. Whether you
might just like we might just have
contextually queued model selection.
Mhm. It's you know, the moment that I
have the slight you know, the slightest
drop in my glucose, then the whole thing
cascades down such that I have the
prioritization of seeking food and I I
don't even have to run the expected free
energy of I could go here, I could go
there, I could go and and what my you
know, how well am I going to do? Yeah.
Rather
I just have this what Now I just at the
very bottom of all that process, I just
have this one
preference, which is eat.
And I think what you know,
something like that might
uh hijack or or shortcut the whole
process leading to like quite low
compute, but actually a pretty robust
um way of like getting adaptation
because
presumably this is something similar to
what a child is doing, right? Like Yeah.
And and I think that kind of works in
terms of like
I don't know, like the simplicity of
children in some ways that they they
sort of cry over anything, which kind of
implies that there is just like a very
simple stimulus-response mapping.
And I wonder whether that could just be
expanded, you know, just more broadly to
model selection. Absolutely. Yeah, I
think that ultimately is probably what's
really happening in biology cuz this is
this also extends across the the
biological
um spectrum. Like animals are very
context or like basically needs-driven.
Like things like attention, all these
basic cognitive faculties are really
enslaved to
effectively the basic things that the
the the lower brain is telling the body
it needs to do like breathing, eating,
um thirst, sleeping. So, I think
ultimately it is some fast
stimulus-response mapping. I think the
only issue with that is it does kind of
it it it seems less principled, right?
It seems like oh, we just have to hack
in a short circuit, and it's not it's
not just like evolving through a neat
process of free energy minimization.
Maybe it is, but it's just happening on
a a slower time scale. Like it's some
slow accumulation of experience
evolutionarily that has trained this
short circuit inference to say, "Oh, I'm
hungry." Yeah. There might have been
some EFE calculation on the part of
evolution to select for Yeah. quite, you
know, uh stimulus-response mappings for
something very like fundamental like
food or sleep or breathing and so on.
Yeah, exactly. Yeah. Okay, cool. Well,
that that's given me lots of ideas I
need to think about. Um It's really
nice, yeah. Final sort of topic I want
to touch on is, you know, just before we
went live, we spoke a little bit about
you being at Verses
uh
full-time. And I I I wanted to sort of
ask, again, I know, speaking of Sanjeev
and others, everything is very under the
wraps, and I and I respect that, and I
don't want Maxwell to come and
you know, shake me. Um but I so I was
curious just a very sort of high-level
you've gone from biology, so thinking
about biological feasibility,
to modeling and artificial intelligence
and trying to ground something in, you
know, trying to take biotic cognition
and say, well, what makes that
intelligent, and then can we replicate
that in silico or
you know, in a robot.
I was just wondering
how biologically feasible are certain
assumptions made by active inference
modelers?
Mhm. For example, active inference
modelers talk about um
uh this again, not exactly my bag, but a
mean field approximation, for example,
where presumably, you know, the the
hidden states or the different tenses
have conditional independence. Mhm. How
you can take that one, you can take any
other just any other assumptions more
broadly, you know, does this seem to you
actually biologically feasible or is it
just like an interesting modeling tool?
No, yeah, I it's actually the those are
those those are probably the most
interesting and important examples of
the assumptions we make. So,
I think the biggest one in one word is
factorization.
The the models both the generative model
that animals have as well as their um Q,
their approximate posterior, which they
optimize using free energy minimization,
those almost necessarily have to be
simplified, in my opinion.
There's some people who believe that the
brain is doing like sampling-based
inference, in which case they can
actually be doing full posteriors, in
which they don't need any
simplifications
in their model of the world. They're
doing full posterior inference on their
model. I don't think that really holds
up cuz it's it's way too slow to be
um useful for for the time scale that
biology needs to work on. So, I think
those assumptions like factorization in
the generative model, those are quite
realistic. Mhm. And factorization in the
posterior, in this approximate
posterior. I think that's actually one
of the coolest things about variational
inference is it seems like something
that brains can do. Mhm. Because once
you make these factorization
assumptions, what it gives you are
updates to your beliefs that are
beautifully local. Like they they only
need nearby information.
And this is kind of the the whole um
uh rallying cry of people like Bert de
Vries
um who work on these message passing and
factor graph schemes. What's beautiful
about that is it's distributed and
local, and that locality inherits from
the fact that we're making
factorizations, or we're making
assumptions of certain variables in my
model or in my beliefs are independent
of each other.
The the the question like a specific
question is is the mean field
factorization appropriate? That one
assumes that all the different state
factors are conditionally independent.
Actually, just fully independent. That
one I think is a is an open question.
And so, there's there's basically a knob
we can turn to from like fully
factorized, where everything's super
cheap and local,
but you're introducing approximation
error. As soon as you start making these
assumptions, your beliefs are not going
to be as good at actually explaining the
data and minimizing free energy. On the
other side, we have fully enumerated
combinatoric entangled beliefs and
explanations for the world, which are
maybe the most accurate, but doing
inference on them is going to be
expensive and take a long time. So, the
open question in my mind for biology,
if we were we're trying to really map
biological processes to like variational
Bayesian inference, is like where on
that sliding scale is biology or our
particular systems. And so, a lot of the
work that we're trying to do at Versus
is basically find good settings of that
knob. Like, we want to figure out what
is a a setting of factorization of
complexity we can build into these
models that they're still sufficiently
expressive and um
and generalizable. They generalize
across context, across tasks,
but they're not computationally insane.
Like, we we need to make things cheap,
and we need to also we would ideally
like to make them cheap enough that we
could imagine neural wetware
implementing them with like local
computation.
Awesome.
Um yeah. Yeah, that's Yes. I mean, I
guess that is the kind of
Well, that's always the accuracy
complexity trade-off, right? I mean,
it's built into the very equations.
Yeah, exactly.
I started in my introduction by asking
about a what I mentioned in my
introduction, apparent teleology.
Mhm. And actually, this was probably the
first question I ever that I had in when
I discovered active inference, what
you know, a year and a bit ago, which is
what is free energy? Why like, is there
a little sensor in the brain that is
like keyed into this like Again, this
this was me being very naive.
Is this like little thing and it's
sensing free energy and it's trying to
get it down to this minimum, which
again, now I think about it, obviously
implies some kind of action policy that
need you know, is descending down free
energy gradients. Mhm. So,
but I it is a naive question, but in
some ways it's useful, I think, because
it feeds into an intuition, which is
human, you know, there's this
long-standing, there was a long-standing
debate about like what life is, right? I
mean, like the elan vitale. Is there
like some special sauce that we put into
humans that just like means that we
self-organize? And I guess this is just
a perennial problem, which is well, why
are we doing this in the first place,
right? The coal tells us that if we are
doing, you know,
if we are if I can say that you're
Connor today and you're Connor tomorrow,
I can kind of describe what you've done,
but like why you do that is a kind of
mystery. And I think some people
intuitively think, well, you know, maybe
there's this adaptive sensor in the
brain which
tracks like this kind of special, you
know, thing called free energy,
which is probably not happening, let's
be honest. Um
And it's obviously an informationally
theoretic term that makes things
compute, tractable from a modeling
perspective. But when you're talking
about putting that into an artificial
agent,
the question that comes to my mind is,
is there anything else that you need to
do? Is there a higher-order prior, for
example, that you need to put into it
that means that it actually will act to
minimize variational free energy, that
it actually will self-organize? Because
there's kind of like why does a computer
work? Like what what I've always just
like what's the kind of fundamental
thing? And maybe in the case of computer
or humans, it's electricity. Is there
anything like that you need to kind of
put in that means that it just doesn't
just sit there and is built with these
beautiful priors, but doesn't really act
in accordance with them? Yeah, yeah. No,
that's a really deep question. I mean,
so at a fundamental level, you're I
totally agree with you that there is no
secret sauce, there's no special signal.
As soon as I've written down any
equation of motion that doesn't explode.
Yeah. any equation of motion for systems
that just generally keep existing.
Another way of saying that is I've
written down a free I can write the
dynamics of that system with some free
energy functional.
So, as designers of artificial systems,
we have the luxury of not having to
write down an equation of motion
in such a particular way that we know if
we backed out the basic mechanics of it,
"Oh, look, it's actually minimizing free
energy." We can start with the free
energy.
Yeah. So, as as artificial engineers, we
can say, "No, we're going to actually
have these things integrate equations of
motion that minimize free energy."
Right.
what we do. But, I But, systems like
self-organizing biological systems,
in the same way
on on the savanna, the giraffes' necks
are not getting longer to reach the
trees because they want to optimize
fitness. That's a post talk like
apparently teleological description for
the dynamics of systems, and then we put
a a sauce on it a a descriptive sauce
called fitness or called natural
selection. That's the exact same thing
with free energy. There's just dynamics,
and then post talk we dress it up with,
"Well, these these dynamics look like
they're actually doing approximate
Bayesian inference." And that's a cool
useful, in my opinion, framing in the
same way natural selection is a cool
useful framing for statistical filtering
of phenotypes over generations.
But, as artificers, as builders and
engineers, we can actually we can
actually write systems that optimize
fitness. We can write an algorithm
We could write a genetic algorithm that
does it automatically kind of. We can
also write an algorithm that directly
surfs a fitness landscape, and in the
same way we can directly write
algorithms that minimize free energy.
The problem is like we now have the
burden of proof of having to write down
a generative model
and to to figure out what the free
energy the best free energy functional
for
for a given um
task is. I think a more like almost like
complex systems
way of designing a system would be to
actually just like design a bunch of
particles in a vat and right and like
basically design physics. Like design a
a particular sandbox of physics that
emergently gives rise to agents that
minimize free energy without actually
plugging that in at the lower level.
Yeah.
But that that's hard though. Yeah,
that's the part that that's kind of
where I was leaning, right? Like
I see, yeah. I guess like
it just it bring it bring does bring
into mind sort of just fundamental
questions of teleology. Yeah. And makes
you think, well, why is physics doing
this in the first place? Um and as you
say, like can we have like if probably
would be in silico, can we get these
kind of particles that just
do it?
And is there a way that we could get to
the bottom of that rung without invoking
another
axiom or another miracle or another
process? And maybe not.
You know, it's um
Yeah, that's Yeah. Is your thinking that
if we did it that way, so we started by
just like writing down very simple
physics of like particles in a vat, and
then we we get the amazing mechanics
emergent for free?
Is cuz I thought about this as well. In
your thinking, is that like is there an
advantage to doing it that way rather
than top-down? Well, I think I think
there's an advantage in the sense that
to my kind of
eyes, there's a slight difference in
between natural selection and varying
and active inference. And that's because
I think um
with natural selection, you get both the
principle and the process.
Mhm. Um now, there are obviously some
axioms and miracles. Now, I'm not a
I'm not a geneticist, so don't shoot you
know, don't shoot the messenger. But
like the basic idea obviously is that
you get the mutations.
And mutations are what drive natural
selection because it leads to a kind of
differentiation within the pool of genes
if you take a very small gene um focused
form of Darwinian Darwinian natural
selection. But that gives you both the
principle, okay, over time, given
mutations, you there will be
optimization for fitness just for free
because you just get obviously you get
the things that are successful in you
know, the genes that permit reproducing
themselves being reproduced and so on.
But with variational free energy and
active inference and the free energy
principle, you get a principle
what you don't necessarily get is the
process, namely
what Karl tells you is
if things persist
this is what they have to this we can
describe them using these mechanics.
Mhm. It doesn't give you
why things persist. Mhm. So that's kind
of what I mean and I do think that if
you had a kind of completely neutral
system because okay,
well the reason why some of these
queries come to mind is because I think
in the older papers, the older active
inference papers, they would very subtly
squeeze in this thing where they would
say, well, there's also the higher-order
prior that or higher-order action policy
to minimize free energy. Mhm.
And then that I think is a very
philosophically fraught thing because
then you go, well, is there a
higher-order policy for that policy?
Mhm.
right?
And evolution obviously grounds some of
this out.
But it makes me think like
sure, it's a really lovely scientific
tool.
But the power is really in the process
theories, whether that's predictive
coding, active inference, variational
message passing, POMDP scheme, or
whatever you want
because you don't get the process for
free from the free energy principle. And
I think in that there's a slight
difference with evolution. Mhm. Totally,
yeah. I I see exactly what you mean,
yeah. I mean, I guess one
I So, it depends on how you define
evolution. I would potentially argue
that natural selection is even happening
in non-biological systems.
And it's just the the process theory
that provides the equivalent of mutation
is maybe slightly different. Right. Um
but I guess you could still say that
well, there's still a mutation. Like
it's it's it's just what do you call
Yeah, it's a change, exactly. And I
think I I my hunch is that something
like that could also be identified for
a variational free energy minimization,
but I think it would be something that
maybe would not be satisfying like
dynamics. Like you need which is another
way of saying change. You need some
function
that maps a state to another state and
that if you iteratively apply that
function, it doesn't diverge to
infinity. Yeah. And I think that would
be like the kind of process theoretic
equivalent of mutation in in natural
selection.
Yeah. I'm I'm sure someone's going to do
it. It probably won't be me. Probably
will be Carl, let's be honest.
Um
Yeah, it comes back to I think to this
idea that Kate was talking about and I
haven't read her book, but I know it's
out, which is that
maybe a slight concern with active
inference and the free energy principle
is that at its very core, it rests on
some kind of determined characteristics.
Mhm. And maybe look, I mean, all
theories have their axioms, right? I
mean, all theories have their miracles
and natural selection definitely has its
miracles. Mhm. But it's very neat and
clever and it all wraps up quite nicely.
And yeah, I think you're absolutely
right that maybe there's a little bit
more work to do to really get the
process of like why things don't just
fall apart. I mean, this was
Schrödinger's big question, right? I
mean Yeah.
and and Carl's big question, but
yeah, I think it's very important for an
audience to realize that when we talk
about active inference being the
overarching theory of everything,
that's probably never never really made
those claims. Yeah, I I totally agree.
We we need we don't have the physics of
why things don't fall apart yet. We've
assumed that that physics works and is
there and then we do the free energy
principle.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah. And which
makes one think and again this is no
disrespect to Carl or you or Maxwell or
anyone who's deeply invested in this
like
exactly how much are we getting out of
the free energy principle? Because I
think Carl himself takes a very
deflationary or tautologist count of the
free energy principle which is a just
says if things persist they act and
perceive like things that would persist
do, right? Like they act things act in
accordance with themselves if they are
to exist as themselves. Mhm.
But as I said, how things do that,
right? You have to do that. If if I make
the fundamental presupposition you are
the same thing today as tomorrow like
you have to at least be obeying by that
principle. Mhm. How you do that?
Well, I guess we'll never Well, we might
know.
Um
Carl, this was really really fun. Um
No, it's these are wonderful deep
questions and I'm actually just very
glad. I think something that people need
to be more of is epistemically humble.
Um and say where they don't know the
answer and I'm very much in admiration
of the fact that you're willing to say
that there are plenty of things that
this community still doesn't know.
Um Oh, thanks. Yeah. So and yeah, the
insights are just wonderful. I mean I My
final question actually is just a
curious curiosity which is you were a
neuroscientist, right? So masters
neuroscience, PhD neuroscience.
Mhm. How on earth
did you learn all the maths and the
physics?
I just out of curiosity. No, that's a
good a great question. Um yeah, so I I
did my bachelor's in kind of more
cognitive neuroscience, doing a lot of
EEG, psycholinguistic stuff. So not
really math heavy at all.
And then in my last year of bachelor's I
took one um computational neuroscience
class at University of Pennsylvania. It
was V.J. Balasubramanian. He was the
teacher.
Um and it just really turned my mind not
only to comp neuro, but then all the
methods that you need to know to do
proper computational neuroscience. And
that kind of just opened the Pandora's
Box a little bit. And then I did a
two-year internship at the National
Institute on Drug Abuse, and we were
doing again like translational
preclinical neuroscience working with
rats and mice.
And just during the evenings during that
that two-year stint, I was taking all
these like machine learning and
computational neuroscience classes that
at the time in like 2015 were still like
free on Coursera. So like Andrew Ng's
course, Geoff Hinton's class. And I
yeah, I just like had to teach myself a
bunch of math. Um, and it was annoying
and hard, but it I think it helped me
catch up a lot to a point where I could
then go and read Karl's papers and
actually like kind of understand what's
going on. Yeah. But it was definitely a
really long and like self-taught
journey. And because of that, I do have
a lot of like foundational gaps in math
that people like Lance DeCoste, like you
can clearly tell by talking to him, he
doesn't have those gaps cuz he has that
that proper education. Well, I'll tell
you there's one man with the biggest gap
of them all, and that's me. So
the PhD will be fun.
Um It'll be great, yeah.
Yeah, we'll we'll be bootstrapping our
way to some kind of mathematical
adequacy. Definitely.
Wonderful. Wonderful, wonderful,
wonderful. So much to think about. Um,
so many wonderful insights and great
intuitions, and yeah, it's just been an
absolute pleasure on my part, and I'm
sure that everyone will benefit
accordingly. Thanks, yeah, it's been so
nice. Thanks for inviting me in the
first place, and it was really a
pleasure talking to you. It was great.
Wonderful. Conor, thank you so so much
again. Thank you.